export const CHRISTIANRELIGIOUSSTUDIESA2015 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Darkness was not created during creation because",
A: "the earth was full of water",
B: "God’s spirit was over the waters",
C: "darkness was already in existence",
D: "God wanted to have day and night",
answer: "C. darkness was already in existence",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The two creation stories agree that",
A: "man and woman were created on the same day",
B: "creation was carried out by spoken word",
C: "there was existing land mass before creation",
D: "created creatures were to be fruitful and multiply",
answer: "B. creation was carried out by spoken word",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Joseph was a good mixer because he",
A: "was loved and pampered by his father",
B: "interacted well with his prison inmates",
C: "rejected Potiphar’s wife’s proposal",
D: "served diligently in Potiphar’s house",
answer: "B. interacted well with his prison inmates",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. “Do you mean to kill me as you killed the Egyptian?” This statement made Moses aware of the fact that",
A: "some Israelites did not like him",
B: "God was sending him to Midian",
C: "Pharaoh was looking for his arrest",
D: "his killing of an Egyptian was known",
answer: "D. his killing of an Egyptian was known",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. God made pharaoh to chase and bring the Israelites back to Egypt so that He would",
A: "show that Moses was his true servant",
B: "destroy first born males of Egyptians",
C: "get glory over Pharaoh and his hosts",
D: "reveal His supernatural powers to the world",
answer: "C. get glory over Pharaoh and his hosts",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The minority report of the twelve spies was presented by",
A: "Caleb and Joshua",
B: "Palti and Gaddiel",
C: "Joshua and Ammiel",
D: "Sethur and Gaddiel",
answer: "A. Caleb and Joshua",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Moses asked God for a new leader for Israel so that Israel might",
A: "have a shepherd",
B: "conquer the Canaanites",
C: "own the Promised Land",
D: "become a great nation",
answer: "A. have a shepherd",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Moses before his death served Israel as",
A: "prophet, liberator and king",
B: "king, priest and warrior",
C: "priest, prophet and deliverer",
D: "strategist, seer and prophet",
answer: "C. priest, prophet and deliverer",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Besides being a true prophetess, Deborah could also be described as a woman of",
A: "love",
B: "glory",
C: "peace",
D: "charity",
answer: "B. glory",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. “Give meat for the priest to roast for he would not accept boiled meat from you but raw.” This request was wrong because in a peace offering,",
A: "meat with blood was unacceptable",
B: "juicy meat went to the worshippers",
C: "the fat were burnt before any distribution",
D: "priests were entitled to the right thigh",
answer: "C. the fat were burnt before any distribution",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following people destroyed Shiloh and captured the Ark?",
A: "Ammonites",
B: "Amalekites",
C: "Palestinians",
D: "Philistines",
answer: "D. Philistines",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Samuel said that the rebellion was as the sin of divination just as stubbornness was as",
A: "iniquity and idolatry",
B: "sinful as disobedience",
C: "iniquity and murder",
D: "sinful as adultery",
answer: "A. iniquity and idolatry",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Has the Lord as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices as in obeying the voice of the Lord? These words were directed to king",
A: "Ahab",
B: "Saul",
C: "Agag",
D: "David,",
answer: "B. Saul",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. After Saul s death on Mount Gilboa, the Philistines",
A: "burnt his body near the tamarisk tree",
B: "sent his head to Dagon their god",
C: "made a sport of him at Bcthshani",
D: "buried his sons in a mass grave.",
answer: "B. sent his head to Dagon their god",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Although David was regarded as a man after God’s heart, he acted badly before God when he",
A: "refused to slay Saul in the wilderness of Kish",
B: "remained at home while his troops were on the battlefield",
C: "imprisoned Nathan for condemning him",
D: "committed sins of adultery and murder.",
answer: "D. committed sins of adultery and murder",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The Hebrew kingdom broke up because of",
A: "Prophet Ahijah’s curse against",
B: "Solomon Solomon’s marriage to foreign women",
C: "Rehoboarns efforts to rule Shechem",
D: "Rehoboam s refusal to grant the Northerners petition.",
answer: "D. Rehoboam’s refusal to grant the Northerners' petition",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Ahab revealed his disregard for the law when he",
A: "get married to Jezebel",
B: "persecuted the prophets of Israel",
C: "appropriated the vineyard of Naboth",
D: "refused to listen to Naboth.",
answer: "C. appropriated the vineyard of Naboth",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Joelah sent the ashes of the burnt vessels of Baal to Bethe! in order to",
A: "desecrate the golden calf being worshipped",
B: "desecrate the place for child sacrifice",
C: "despoil the high places of Asherah",
D: "consecrate that place for Yahweh worship,",
answer: "A. desecrate the golden calf being worshipped",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. King Nebuchadnezzar mounted his golden image on/at the",
A: "plain of Dura.",
B: "the plain of Jericho",
C: "the sea of Arabab",
D: "Susa of Babylon.",
answer: "A. plain of Dura",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Daniel disobeyed King Darius by",
A: "refusing to honour the Persian gods,",
B: "refusing to be made president of the Satraps",
C: "celebrating Jewish festival in a foreign land",
D: "praying three times daily for thirty days.",
answer: "D. praying three times daily for thirty days",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The Judean King who revolted against Babylon after serving her for three",
A: "Jehoahaz",
B: "Jehorakim",
C: "Jehoiachin",
D: "Zedekiah.",
answer: "D. Zedekiah",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Nehemiah showed concern for his nation by",
A: "reviving Yahweh worship",
B: "rebuilding the temple",
C: "reconstructing Jerusalem walls",
D: "leading exiles home",
answer: "C. reconstructing Jerusalem walls",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The tribe which led the Jews in rebuilding the temple were",
A: "Judah and Benjamin",
B: "Levi and Gad",
C: "Ephraim and Manasseh",
D: "Reuben and Zebulun.",
answer: "A. Judah and Benjamin",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Amos satirically invited the Jews to come to Bethel and Gilgal in order to",
A: "Repent",
B: "Worship",
C: "Transgress",
D: "pacify.",
answer: "C. Transgress",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Hosea described the relationship between God and Israel as",
A: "a covenant contract",
B: "a marriage bond",
C: "a marriage reunion",
D: "an agreement bond.",
answer: "B. a marriage bond",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Jesus’ baptism was significant because it",
A: "initiated him into Judaism",
B: "cleansed Him from sin",
C: "awakened the messianic spirit in Him",
D: "marked the call into the messianic ministry",
answer: "D. marked the call into the messianic ministry",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. ‘you are the son of God, throw yourself down from here’. This temptation implies that Jesus should",
A: "win followers through the use of spectacular miracles",
B: "win converts through the supply at basic needs",
C: "allow angels minister unto Him",
D: "use scriptures to overcome the devil",
answer: "A. win followers through the use of spectacular miracles",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The two Old Testament books that were used in the temptation stories were",
A: "Genesis and Proverbs",
B: "Leviticus and Lamentation",
C: "Numbers and Ecclesiastes",
D: "Deuteronomy and Psalms,",
answer: "D. Deuteronomy and Psalms",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. “For he was astonished, and all that were With him, at the catch offish which they had taken” The people being referred to in the text were",
A: "Matthew John and Andrew",
B: "Matthias, John and Peter",
C: "James Peter and John",
D: "Simon, Andrew and Thomas",
answer: "C. James, Peter and John",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Jesus taught that Christians should forgive their neighbours’ sins",
A: "three times only",
B: "seventy times seven times,",
C: "seventy-seven times seven",
D: "as many times as possible",
answer: "B. seventy times seven times",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. In the garden at Gethsemane. Jesus",
A: "Was arrested",
B: "Was crucified",
C: "rebuked Judas Iscariot",
D: "prayed for peace",
answer: "D. prayed for peace",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. During Jesus met some people discovered that Peter was Jesus follower because of his",
A: "Pharisaic attire",
B: "Galilean accent",
C: "attack on the maid",
D: "anger against the Jews",
answer: "B. Galilean accent",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following incidents occurred during Jesus’ trial before Caiaphas?",
A: "The preference of Barabbas to Jesus",
B: "The question at payment of tribute",
C: "Accusations of Jesus as a rioter",
D: "The seeking of false Witness against Jesus",
answer: "D. The seeking of false witnesses against Jesus",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Discipleship requires self-denial and complete",
A: "Tolerance",
B: "Forgiveness",
C: "Commitment",
D: "purification.",
answer: "C. Commitment",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. This is the king of the Jews. This inscription on the cross was meant to show Jesus",
A: "Charge",
B: "Punishment",
C: "Victory",
D: "Messiaship",
answer: "A. Charge",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. How many groups of people mocked at Jesus on the cross according to St. Marks gospel?",
A: "Two",
B: "Three",
C: "Four",
D: "Five",
answer: "B. Three",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. “Mary Magdalene and the other Mary went to see the sepulchre.” The other Mary” according to ST Mark was the mother of",
A: "James and Joses",
B: "James and John",
C: "Simon and Andrew",
D: "Thomas and John Mark.",
answer: "A. James and Joses",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. The resurrection story encourages Christians to believe that the Lord they adore is",
A: "still alive today",
B: "a Miracle working God",
C: "Lord over evils",
D: "powerful and just.",
answer: "A. still alive today",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. As a result of Peter’s speech on Pentecost day",
A: "The dispute Over drunkenness was resolved",
B: "the prophecies of Joel were vindicated",
C: "the religious leaders accepted Jesus’ resurrection",
D: "many Jewish souls joined Christianity.",
answer: "D. many Jewish souls joined Christianity",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. To which religious party did Gamaliel belong?",
A: "The Zealots",
B: "Sadducees.",
C: "Pharisees.",
D: "Herod",
answer: "C. Pharisees",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. And we witnesses to these things, and so is the Holy Spirit Who? God has given to those who obey him “These things” in the disciples statement before the Sanhedrin refers to",
A: "the election of Matthias.",
B: "Outpouring of the holy spirit",
C: "the miracles and teaching of Jesus",
D: "death and resurrection of Jesus Christ.",
answer: "D. death and resurrection of Jesus Christ",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Stephen was appointed as a deacon to",
A: "preach to the gentile world.",
B: "perform signs and wonders of Jesus,",
C: "cater for the poor and needy,",
D: "defend Christianity as a true religion",
answer: "C. cater for the poor and needy",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. The importance of the parable of the unmerciful servant is that Christians should",
A: "allow mercy to take precedence over justice.",
B: "avoid discrimination against one another,",
C: "be faithful and not to betray their trust,",
D: "use wealth diligently and honestly.",
answer: "A. allow mercy to take precedence over justice",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The visitors of Peter after his vision at Joppa were from",
A: "Jerusalem.",
B: "Samaria",
C: "Caesarea.",
D: "Antioch",
answer: "C. Caesarea",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. When Rhoda reported that Peter was at the door, the inmates retorted that",
A: "you are a liar",
B: "you are mad",
C: "Peter is dead",
D: "Peter is alive",
answer: "B. you are mad",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. James maintained that the double-minded man would not have his prayers answered because he",
A: "is unstable in all his ways",
B: "asks for things with selfish motives",
C: "prayers with unforgiving hearts",
D: "intercedes with a sinful heart",
answer: "A. is unstable in all his ways",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following according to James is an important factor for effective prayer?",
A: "Love",
B: "Faith",
C: "Hope",
D: "Mercy",
answer: "B. Faith",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Partiality according to James is manifested in the Church through",
A: "Discrimination.",
B: "Charity.",
C: "Affection",
D: "Impartiality.",
answer: "A. Discrimination",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. To be a good citizen, Peter advised believers’ to honour all men and",
A: "live as free men",
B: "love the brotherhood",
C: "obey their lawful master",
D: "love reading the scriptures",
answer: "B. love the brotherhood",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Peter encouraged the church to humble themselves before God so that He would",
A: "exonerate them,",
B: "not punish them,",
C: "exalt them,",
D: "not disown them.",
answer: "C. exalt them",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]